foreign
start with a length one line segment and
use a straight edge Encompass to
construct a perpendicular length one
line segment connect the endpoints like
this and label the length of the
hypotenuse of this right triangle by a
because the triangle satisfies the
Pythagorean theorem we see that a equals
the square root of two
now use the Straight Edge Encompass to
draw a line segment of length one that
is perpendicular to the diagonal of
length root 2. connect the endpoints
again and now we have a new length a and
this time by the Pythagorean theorem we
can determine that a squared is 3 so
that a is the square root of 3. let's
repeat this process one more time use
the Straight Edge Encompass to create a
circle of radius 1 and then a line
segment of length one that is
perpendicular to the line segment of
length root 3. connect the endpoints
like this and use the Pythagorean
theorem to determine that the length of
the hypotenuse of that new right
triangle is the square root of four
using a straight edge Encompass we have
constructed line segments of length
square root of 2 square root of 3 and
square root of 4 but there's no reason
to stop there we can keep applying the
exact same process over and over again
to the new links that we create and we
see that we can create line segments of
length square root of 5 square root of 6
and square root of 7.
how far can we take this process can we
just keep going forever the object shown
here is the first six stages of the
Spiral of theodorus
the spiral can be extended indefinitely
but just for our purposes let's take it
out to I don't know how about n equals
one thousand we'll see the first 1000
levels of the Spiral of theodorus and
along the way we're constructing the
square root of n for every single n
value between two and a thousand
once we get to the end of our spiral as
we've done right here we see that the
final line that we've drawn has a length
of size square root of one thousand
for appearances we can construct the
circle with a radius of square root 1000
and draw a radius in the same direction
as our original length one line segment
while this may not be the most efficient
way to get the length of square root of
1000 using this process we can construct
the square root of n for any positive
integer n this means that the spiral of
theodorus constructs square roots and
shows us how to prove that square roots
are constructable using Straight Edge
Encompass using proof by induction